Guide to the Boehm Foundation (New York, N.Y.) Records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Boehm Foundation (New York, N.Y.) Records,
1963-2004
[Bulk dates: 1993-2002].
Boehm Foundation (New York, N.Y.)
18 linear ft. (36 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5486657
MS#1425
This collection consists of the records of the Boehm Foundation, a philanthropic organization that provided grants primarily to fund groups devoted to promoting democratic government and civil rights. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, grant proposals, and printed materials related to these individual grants and the grantee organizations. There is also a small amount of administrative material, including financial reports, internal memos, and board meeting minutes.
History
The Boehm Foundation was born in 1962 when Louis Boehm, a successful lawyer and real estate investor from New York City, died and set aside one million dollars of his estate to aid future "deserving scholars." Boehm's son, Robert, and several family friends used the bequest to start the Louis Boehm Foundation in 1963, the same year that Robert and his wife Frances organized the Lillian Boehm Foundation. Named after and funded in part by Robert's mother, the Lillian Boehm Foundation was established, according to an early mission statement, in order "to assist in efforts to bring about important and meaningful social change... in the interest of a more democratic society." The Louis and Lillian Boehm Foundations merged in 1978 to become simply the "Boehm Foundation," and the goals of aiding young scholars and activists as well as promoting social change and democracy continued to guide the Foundation's business through 2004 when it distributed its last grants.
The progressive nature of the Boehm Foundation was somewhat ironic considering that Louis Boehm was relatively conservative in comparison to his son. At one point in the 1930s, for example, he even helped Robert travel to the Soviet Union in the hopes of "disillusioning" him about the potential of radical politics. Yet despite Louis' best efforts, Robert became ever more committed to the political left. After graduating first from Dartmouth and then Columbia University Law School, Robert went to work in his father's law firm. While there he met his future wife, Frances, who was as a secretary in the firm. Their first date was at a 1938 rally held in Madison Square Garden where the featured speaker was Earl Browder, the head of the American Communist Party. Known by acquaintances as Bob and Fran throughout their lives, they married in 1939.
Not only did 1938 see Bob and Fran Boehm meet, it also saw Bob join the National Lawyers' Guild (NLG), an interracial coalition of progressive lawyers that was founded in 1937 in order to defend civil liberties. Boehm remained a member of the NLG throughout his life, but his role as a legal activist was most prominent in his close association with the Center for Constitutional Rights (CCR), an advocacy group that was founded to aid the United States Civil Rights Movement. (It later defended rioters at Attica prison in 1971, protested United States intervention in Central America, and supported prisoners held by the US at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, among other causes.) Active with CCR from its founding in 1966, Boehm was its chairperson of the board for most of the 1990s and until his death in 2006. Though not a lawyer herself, Fran Boehm became a fixture at many of the trials, conferences, and protests in which these and other groups were involved, and her legacy of activism developed along with Bob Boehm's through the US civil rights, women's rights, and peace movements of the second half of the twentieth century.
Bob and Fran started the Boehm Foundation within this context of political, legal, and social activism. Because the Foundation remained a small organization to the end, the Boehm's backgrounds and contemporaneous activities proved highly influential in determining the course of its development. Throughout the Boehm Foundation's life, it often gave far more substantial grants to groups like the NLG and CCR than to its other projects. As one brochure from the 1990s put it, the Boehm Foundation "provided substantial and on-going support to several organizations with which it has special historical relationships," while its regular grants were evaluated on an annual basis and were generally for considerably lower dollar amounts. Such "special historical relationships" were ensured by the fact that in the early years of the Louis Boehm Foundation, Bob Boehm looked to friends like Bernie Fischman--his one-time law partner--to serve as trustees and help identify worthy projects for the Foundation's attention. Frances had been a trustee of the Lillian Boehm Foundation from its beginning, and she remained a trustee of the newly-formed Boehm Foundation in 1978. In part to ensure the familial nature of the Foundation, the Boehms' three daughters, Diane Boehm, Nancy Boehm (later Boehm-Coster), and Wendy Olesker were all named replacement trustees in 1978 on the contingency that one of the current trustees died.
The late 1970s were an important turning point for the Boehm Foundation, and not simply because of the 1978 merger. It was in these years that Nancy Boehm-Coster started to take an interest in the operations of the Foundation, eventually becoming a trustee in 1980. Bob Boehm later said that it was Nancy's insistence around this time that the organization should become "more formal" that really spurred the development of the Foundation from an ad hoc family institution to a professional philanthropic group.
As Bob Boehm described it, Nancy felt that "the people who... [ran the Foundation] should be changed every few years, and there shouldn't be a monopoly of just those particular people, and we should have regular elections, and that women should be included on the board, not just men." In addition to these changes, Nancy Boehm-Coster became the first Executive Director of the Boehm Foundation in 1984. In this role, she was responsible for processing grant applications, organizing and running board meetings, and corresponding with grantees, among other tasks. She held the role until her death from cancer in 1991. Upon her death, Judy Austermiller--a Boehm Foundation trustee since 1984--took over as the only other Executive Director the Foundation ever had, serving (except for a one-year sabbatical during which June Makela was the acting Executive Director) until its dissolution in 2004.
As part of the Boehm Foundation's formalization during this period, it began to more actively seek new applicants and organizations to aid. An important aspect of this project was the Foundation's efforts to better define its mission. As one call for grants from the early 1990s explained, the Boehm Foundation's two main principles are that "the educational, spiritual and creative aspects of humankind can only be developed when the full range of human rights are protected and respected" and that "the best interests of a society are advanced in an atmosphere which encourages the free flow of ideas and information and which discourages secrecy and censorship." Fueled by a belief that "it is organized and collective efforts" as opposed to individual action "that will most effectively and meaningfully fulfill these aims," the Boehm Foundation prioritized projects which were "advancing democracy and human rights in the U.S." and "advancing peace and international human rights." Insistent throughout the late 1980s and early 1990s--as it had been from its origin--that the Foundation should focus on helping multiple emerging and often small groups that could find funding from few other sources, the brochure further explained that the Foundation's grants ranged from "$500 to $15,000" and that "the average grant is $3,500."
By the 1990s, the Boehm Foundation was giving out sixty-five to eighty grants per year (not including its "special projects"). But by mid-1999, Austermiller sensed that a reevaluation of the Boehm Foundation's priorities might be in order. As she noted in an internal memo from August of that year, two changes had begun to shape the Foundation: as more groups applied for funding each year, the backlog of unevaluated applications was growing larger and larger; at the same time, the Boehms were increasingly giving out larger grants, both through the Boehm Foundation and in their private gifts. With these observations, a series of board meetings and retreats were held to discuss the future of the Boehm Foundation.
Out of this evaluative process came the last incarnation of the Boehm Foundation. In early 2001, the Foundation sent out a letter to grant applicants explaining that the Foundation was now channeling its gifts to two types of groups: "grassroots organizations that are developing new leadership through work on specific public/private policy campaigns" and "statewide, regional or national organizations that provide support to progressive grassroots public policy campaigns." The first of these two grant categories were known as "New Leaders Grants" and were intended to be "two-year general support grants ranging in size from $7,500 to $10,000 per year." Grants falling into the second category were called "Capacity Building Grants" and were designed as "two- or three-year grants ranging in size from $25,000 to $50,000 per year." The Foundation committed to making approximately twelve New Leaders grants and two Capacity Building grants annually.
In a sense, the creation of the New Leaders and Capacity Building programs represented a formalization of past practices rather than a distinct change in the mission of the Boehm Foundation. After all, it had often given large multi-year grants to a few organizations in the past while focusing the bulk of its resources on an assortment of smaller groups. In retrospect, however, the creation of these two programs--and the much larger amounts of their grants--suggests that the trustees of the Boehm Foundation recognized at least the possibility that the Foundation might be nearing the end of its life. Indeed, it was at about the same time that the Foundation was formally instituting these guidelines that the Boehms and Judy Austermiller also began to discuss the long-term future of the organization.
Bob Boehm turned 86 in 2000, and in that year the Foundation commissioned an independent study to suggest ways for the final disposition of its holdings. Though several plans that would have enabled the continuation of the Boehm Foundation in the event of its founders' deaths (including the establishment of a permanent endowment) were proposed, the Boehms had settled by 2003 on dismantling the Boehm Foundation. The final installments of its multi-year grants were disbursed in 2004, more than forty years after the Louis Boehm and Lillian Boehm Foundations were established.
Even without the Boehm Foundation, Bob and Fran continued to give large gifts to favored organizations and stayed active in many of their other pursuits, especially the Center for Constitutional Rights. Indeed, Bob remained the chairperson of the board of CCR until just a few months before his death. After a lifetime devoted to progressive causes, Frances Boehm died in February 2006; Robert Boehm followed in December of that year.
Scope and Content
The Boehm Foundation Records consist overwhelmingly of files pertaining to the grants that the Foundation administered. While the subject matter of these files varies somewhat, almost all of the files contain correspondence between the Foundation and the grantee organization. Many of them include supplemental information from the grantee organization such as annual reports, brochures, flyers, publications, etc., which in most cases indicate the ways in which the Foundation's grant was spent.
In addition to material related to specific grant projects, there is also a small but significant amount of the Boehm Foundation's administrative files. These include financial reports, internal memos, board meeting agendas, letter templates, grant application forms, and brochures, among other material.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Administrative Records, 1963-2003 (1979-2003)
Series II: Special Projects, 1982-2003
Series III: Annual Grants, 1988-2004
Subseries 1: Summary Material, 1994-1999
Subseries 2: Annual Grants, 1988-2003
Subseries 3: New Leaders Grants, 2001-2004
Subseries 4: Capacity Building Grants, 1999-2004
Subjects
Boehm Foundation (New York, N.Y.); Center for Constitutional Rights (New York, N.Y.); Institute for Policy Studies.; Lawyers' Committee on Nuclear Policy.; Austermiller, Judy.; Boehm, Frances.; Boem, Robert.; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations.; Non-profit institutions in America.; Philanthropists.
Access Restrictions
Thuis collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Gift of Robert L. Boehm and Frances Boehm, 2004.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1963-2003 (1979-2003)
  This series is composed largely of financial records of the Boehm Foundation, including its annual reports and dockets from the quarterly board meetings at which grant decisions were finalized. It also includes a number of documents which detail the various trust arrangements related to the Foundation and the membership of its board of trustees. Lastly, this series contains a variety of material related to the business of running the Foundation, including its promotional materials (with grant guidelines), letter templates, internal memos, and staff lists, among other items. Material in this series is organized by subject, with one exception: a binder included in the collection has been deconstructed for preservation purposes, but its varied contents remain together.
  - Administrative Binder--Grant Guidelines, Correspondence, Letter Templates, Minutes, Board Member Lists, and Awards, circa 1991-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Financial Statements, 1980-2001, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Annual Reports, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Biographies, Reports, Correspondence, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Board of Trustees Memoranda, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minutes (with Dockets), 1981-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Boehm Foundation Financial Holdings, 1978 December 27 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dockets, 1984-1990, (7 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 4-10)
  - Dockets, 1991-1997, (7 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Dockets, 1998-2002 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - Grant Guidelines, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Grant Guidelines (Revised) and Long-Term Plan Development, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Grant Lists, 1979-1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Grant Lists, 1989-2001
    - 1989-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1996-2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Trust Agreements and Financial Information, 1963-2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series II: Special Projects, 1982-2003
  While the vast majority of the grants given out by the Boehm Foundation from 1982-2003 were small grants that were up for renewal on an annual basis, there were a few groups that the Foundation funded at a far higher monetary level and in multi-year terms. The special consideration given by the Boehm Foundation to the organizations in this series can in most cases be explained by the personal relationship Robert Boehm shared with these organizations. For example, he was the long-time chairperson of the board for the Center for Constitutional Rights and served for a time as the treasurer of the Lawyers' Committee on Nuclear Policy. Two of the long-term projects appearing in this series were scholarship funds established in the name of Boehm's daughter, Nancy Boehm-Coster, after her death in 1991.
  Material in this series is organized alphabetically according to the names of the programs or organizations funded by the Boehm Foundation.
  - Center for Constitutional Rights, 1988-2003
    - 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 2001-2003 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Columbia Law School Summer Human Rights Internship Program, 1986-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - CUNY Law School at Queens College, 1990-2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dartmouth College Boehm Foundation Scholarship, 1992-2002 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Dartmouth College Nancy Boehm Coster Public Policy Career Encouragement Program, 1994-2000, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Institute for Policy Studies, 1982-2000
    - 1982-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1993-1997 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1997-2000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Folder (Containing Programs, News Clippings, Etc.), circa 1996-1999 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Lawyers' Committee on Nuclear Policy, 1987-2001
    - 1987-1997 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1997-2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - State University of New York at Albany Fellowship on Women and Public Policy--Nancy Boehm Coster Fellows, 1990-1994, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
- Series III: Annual Grants, 1988-2004
  This series comprises both the bulk of material contained in this collection and the primary business conducted by the Boehm Foundation: records concerning the Foundation's disbursement of small grants to a variety of non-profit organizations pursuing social and political change. The records consist largely of correspondence between grantee organizations and the Boehm Foundation. Since many groups included supplementary material in their correspondence such as annual reports or news clippings, this material is also found throughout the series.
  - Subseries 3.1: Summary Material, 1994-1999
    This subseries provides an insight into both the administrative side of the Boehm Foundation and its grant-giving process, by including checklists for each grantee organization of relevant data about their application such as the date it was submitted and the amount of money given by the Boehm Foundation. Internal Revenue Service rulings certifying that the grantee organizations had non-profit status for the purposes of the Boehm Foundation's gifts are also present in many cases.
    The material in this subseries is organized in chronological order.
    - Grant Checklists, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Grant Checklists, A-I 1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Grant Checklists, L-Y, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Grant Checklists, A-K, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Grant Checklists, L-Y, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Grant Checklists, A-K, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Grant Checklists, L-Y, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 3.2: Annual Grants, 1988-2002
    The Boehm Foundation gave out hundreds of small (usually valued at $5,000 or less) one-year grants from 1988-2003. This subseries contains information pertaining to those grants, including a substantial amount of correspondence between the Boehm Foundation and their various grantee organizations. The records in this subseries include letters of inquiry, grant proposals, progress reports, and letters of gratitude. Many of the grantee organizations also included with their correspondence supplementary materials such as publications, flyers, or news clippings relating to the group. In most cases, these materials have been arranged alongside the letters with which they were enclosed.
    The material in this subseries is arranged according to the individual grants made by the Boehm Foundation in any given year. Therefore, although correspondence about a given grant might extend to both the year before it was given (often the case with letters of inquiry) and the year after (often the case with status reports), all of the information about any particular grant is arranged according to the grantee organization's name in the year in which the Boehm Foundation made its gift. Please note that any grantee organization named after a person takes the last name of the person for purposes of alphabetization. For example, the "Paul Robeson Fund for Independent Media" is alphabetized under "R," for "Robeson."
    - Annual Grants, A-C, 1988-1990
      - Achievement Scholarship Program, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Africa Fund, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Agendas International, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - American Friends of the Hebrew University, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - American-Israeli Civil Liberties Coalition, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Association for Civil Rights in Israel, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Bill of Rights Foundation, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Brecht Forum, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - CCCO, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Center for Democratic Renewal, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Center for International Policy, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Center for Minority Achievement, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Center for Preventive Psychiatry, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - James Earl Chaney Foundation, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Chile Humanitarian Aid, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Christic Institute, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Annual Grants, C-H, 1987-1991
      - Columbia Law School Paul Robeson Scholarship in Minority Legal Studies, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Community Service Society, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Council on Economic Priorities, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Council on Hemispheric Affairs, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Daisy Foundation, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Disarm Education Fund, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Educators for Social Responsibility, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Empowerment Project/"COVERUP: Behind the Iran Contra Affair," 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - El Salvador Public Information Campaign, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - First District Appellate Project, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Friends of New Outlook, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Friends of Ruth Messenger, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Funding Exchange, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Givat Haviva, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Andrew Goodman Foundation, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Grass Roots Events, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Human Serve, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Hunter College, 1988-1991 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Annual Grants, I-O, 1988-1991
      - Independent Commission of Inquiry on the U.S. Invasion of Panama, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Institute for Security and Cooperation in Outer Space, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Institute for Technology & Development, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Institute for Women's Policy Research, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Instituto Puertorriqueño de Derechos Civiles, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - International Foundation for Global Economic Challenge, circa 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Interreligious Foundation for Community Organization, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - "In the Public Interest," 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Jobs With Peace Educational Fund, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Lawyers Committee on Nuclear Policy/Robert Wm. Jolly, Jr., 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Long Island Alliance to Prevent Nuclear War, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Meiklejohn Civil Liberties Institute, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Mental Health Law Project, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Montefiore Medical Center, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - National Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)